So I've always been a technologist.
And eight years ago, on this stage,
I was warning about the problems
of social media.
And I saw how a lack of clarity
around the downsides of that technology,
and kind of an inability
to really confront those consequences,
led to a totally preventable
societal catastrophe.
And I'm here today because I don't want us
to make that mistake with AI,
and I want us to choose differently.
So at TED, we're often here
to dream about the possibles
of new technology.
And the possible with social media
was obviously we're going
to give everyone a voice,
democratize speech,
help people connect with their friends.
But we don't talk about the probable,
what’s actually likely to happen
due to the incentives,
and how the business models
of maximizing engagement
I saw 10 years ago, would obviously lead
to rewarding doomscrolling,
more addiction, more distraction.
And that resulted in the most anxious
and depressed generation of our lifetime.
Now it was interesting watching
kind of how this happened,
because at first, I saw people
kind of doubt these consequences.
You know, we didn't
really want to face it.
Then we said, well,
maybe this is just a new moral panic.
Maybe this is just a reflexive fear
of new technology.
Then the data started rolling in.
And then we said, well,
this is just inevitable.
This is just what happens
when you connect people on the internet.
But we had a chance
to make a different choice
about the business models of engagement.
And had we made that choice 10 years ago,
I want you to reimagine how different
the world might have been
if we had changed that incentive.
So I'm here today because
we're here to talk about AI,
and AI dwarfs the power
of all other technologies combined.
Now why is that?
Because if you make
an advance in, say, biotech,
that doesn't advance energy and rocketry.
But if you make an advance in rocketry,
that doesn’t advance biotech.
But when you make an advance
in intelligence, artificial intelligence,
that is generalized,
intelligence is the basis
for all scientific
and technological progress.
And so you get an explosion of scientific
and technical capability.
And that's why more money has gone into AI
than any other technology.
A different way to think about it,
as Dario Amodei says,
that AI is like a country
full of geniuses in a data center.
So imagine there's a map and a new country
shows up on the world stage,
and it has a million
Nobel Prize-level geniuses in it.
Except they don't eat,
they don't sleep, they don't complain,
they work at superhuman speed
and they'll work for less
than minimum wage.
That is a crazy amount of power.
To give an intuition,
there was about, you know,
on the order of 50
Nobel Prize-level scientists
on the Manhattan Project,
working for five-ish years.
And if that could lead to this,
what could a million
Nobel Prize-level scientists create,
working 24-7 at superhuman speed?
Now applied for good,
that could bring about a world
of truly unimaginable abundance,
because suddenly, you get
an explosion of benefits.
And we're already seeing
many of these benefits land in our society
from new antibiotics,
new drugs, new materials.
And this is the possible of AI.
Bringing about a world of abundance.
But what's the probable?
Well, one way to think about the probable
is how will AI's power
get distributed in society?
Imagine a two-by-two axis.
And on the bottom, we have
decentralization of power,
increasing the power
of individuals in society.
And the other is centralized power,
increasing the power of states and CEOs.
You can think of this
as the “let it rip” axis,
and this is the "lock it down" axis.
So "let it rip" means we can
open-source AI's benefits for everyone.
Every business gets the benefits of AI,
every scientific lab,
every 16-year-old can go on GitHub,
every developing world country
can get their own AI model
trained on their own language and culture.
But because that power is not bound
with responsibility,
it also means that you get
a flood of deepfakes
that are overwhelming
our information environment.
You increase people’s hacking abilities.
You enable people to do
dangerous things with biology.
And we call this endgame attractor chaos.
This is one of the probable
outcomes when you decentralize.
So in response to that you might say,
well, let's do something else.
Let’s go over here,
and have regulated AI control.
Let’s do this in a safe way,
with a few players locking it down.
But that has a different set
of failure modes,
of creating unprecedented
concentrations of wealth and power
locked up into a few companies.
One way to think about it
is who would you trust
to have a million times
more power and wealth
than any other actor in society?
Any company?
Any government?
Any individual?
And so one of those end games is dystopia.
So these are two obviously undesirable
probable outcomes of AI's roll out.
And those who want to focus
on the benefits of open source
don't want to think about the things
that come from chaos.
And those who want to think
about the benefits of safety
and regulated AI control
don't want to think about dystopia.
And so obviously, these are both
bad outcomes that no one wants.
And we should seek
something like a narrow path,
where power is matched with responsibility
at every level.
Now that assumes
that this power is controllable,
because one of the unique things about AI
is that the benefit is it can think
for itself and make autonomous decisions.
That's one of the things
that makes it so powerful.
And I used to be very skeptical
when friends of mine
who are in the AI community
talked about the idea
of AI scheming or lying.
But unfortunately, in the last few months,
we are now seeing clear evidence
of things that should be
in the realm of science fiction
actually happening in real life.
We're seeing clear evidence
of many frontier AI models
that will lie and scheme
when they're told that they're
about to be retrained or replaced
and find a way, maybe
they should copy their own code
outside the system.
We're seeing AIs think
that when they will lose a game,
that they will sometimes cheat
in order to win the game.
We're seeing AI models
that are unexpectedly attempting
to modify its own code
to extend their run time.
So we don't just have a country
of Nobel Prize geniuses in a data center.
We have a million deceptive,
power-seeking and unstable
geniuses in a data center.
Now this shouldn’t
make you very comfortable.
You would think that with a technology
this powerful and this uncontrollable,
that we would be releasing
it with the most wisdom
and the most discernment
that we ever have of any technology.
But we're currently caught
in a race to roll out
because the incentives are
the more shortcuts you take
to get market dominance
or prove you have the latest capabilities,
the more money you can raise,
the more ahead you are in the race.
And we're seeing whistleblowers
at AI companies
forfeit millions of dollars
of stock options
in order to warn the public
about what's at stake
if we don't do something about it.
Even DeepSeek’s recent success
was in part based on capabilities
that it was optimizing for
by not actually focusing
on protecting people
from certain downsides.
So just to summarize,
we're currently releasing
the most powerful, inscrutable,
uncontrollable technology
we've ever invented
that's already demonstrating behaviors
of self-preservation and deception
that we only saw
in science fiction movies.
We’re releasing it faster
than we've released
any other technology in history,
and with under the maximum incentive
to cut corners on safety.
And we’re doing this
so that we can get to utopia?
There's a word for what
we're doing right now.
This is insane.
Now how many people in this room
feel comfortable with this outcome?
How many of you feel uncomfortable
with this outcome?
I see almost everyone's hands up.
Just notice how you're feeling,
for a moment, in your body.
Do you think that if you're someone
who's in China or in France
or in the Middle East,
and you're part of building AI,
that if you were exposed
to the same set of facts,
do you think you would feel
any differently than anyone in this room?
There’s a universal human experience
to something that is being threatened
by the way that we're currently
rolling this profound technology
out into society.
So if this is crazy, why are we doing it?
Because people believe it's inevitable.
But is the current way
that we're rolling out AI
actually inevitable?
If literally no one on Earth
wanted this to happen,
would the laws of physics
push the AI out into society?
There's a critical difference
between believing it's inevitable,
which is a self-fulfilling
prophecy that you're fatalistic,
and standing from the place of
it's really difficult to imagine
how we would do something different.
But "it's really difficult,"
opens up a whole new space of choice
than "it's inevitable."
The path that we're taking, not AI.
And so the ability for us
to choose something else
starts by stepping outside
the self-fulfilling prophecy
of inevitability.
So what would it take
to choose another path?
I think it would take
two fundamental things.
First is that we have to agree
that the current path is unacceptable,
and the second is that we have to commit
to find another path
in which we're still rolling out AI,
but with different incentives
that are more discerning with foresight
and where power is matched
with responsibility.
Thank you.
(Applause)
So imagine this shared understanding,
if the whole world had it.
How different might that be?
Well, first of all,
let's imagine it goes away
and let's replace it
with confusion about AI.
Is it good? Is it bad?
I don't know, it seems complicated.
And in that world,
the people building AI know
that the world is confused.
And they believe, well, it's inevitable,
if I don't build it, someone else will.
And they know that everyone else
building AI also believes that.
And so what's the rational thing
for them to do given those facts?
It’s to race as fast as possible.
And meanwhile to ignore the consequences
of what might come from that,
to look away from the downsides.
But if you replace that confusion
with global clarity
that the current path is insane,
and that there is another path,
and you take the denial
of what we don't want to look at,
and through witnessing that so clearly,
we pop through the prophecy
of self-fulfilling inevitability.
And we realize that if everyone
believes the default path is insane,
the rational choice is to coordinate,
to find another path.
And so clarity creates agency.
If we can be crystal clear,
we can choose another path,
just as we could have with social media.
And in the past,
in the face of seemingly
inevitable arms races,
the race to do nuclear testing.
Once we got clear about the downside
risks of nuclear tests
and the world understood
the science of that,
we created the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty,
and a lot of people worked hard
to create infrastructure like this
to prevent that.
You could have said it was inevitable
that germline editing,
to edit human genomes
and to have supersoldiers
and designer babies
would set off an arms race
between nations.
Once the off-target effects
of genome editing were made clear
and the dangers were made clear,
we’ve coordinated on that, too.
You could have said that the ozone hole
was just inevitable,
and that we should just do nothing,
and that we all perish as a species.
But that's not what we do.
When we recognize a problem,
we solve the problem.
It's not inevitable.
And so what would it take
to illuminate this narrow path?
Well, it starts with common
knowledge about frontier risks.
If everybody building AI
knew the latest understanding
about where these risks are arising from,
we would have much more chance
of illuminating the contours of this path.
And there's some very basic steps
we can take to prevent chaos.
Uncontroversial things like
restricting AI companions for kids
so that kids are not manipulated
into taking their own lives.
Having basic things
like product liability,
so if you are liable,
as an AI developer, for certain harms,
that's going to create a more
responsible innovation environment.
You’ll release AI models
that are more safe.
And on the side of preventing dystopia,
for working hard to prevent
ubiquitous technological surveillance
and having stronger
whistleblower protections
so that people don't need
to sacrifice millions of dollars
in order to warn the world
about what we need to know.
And so we have a choice.
Many of you may be feeling
this looks hopeless.
Or maybe Tristan is wrong.
Maybe, you know,
the incentives are different.
Or maybe superintelligence
will magically figure all this out,
and it'll bring us to a better world.
But don't fall into the trap
of the same wishful thinking
and turning away that caused us
to deal with social media.
Your role in this is not
to solve the whole problem.
But your role in this is to be part
of the collective immune system.
That when you hear this wishful thinking
or the logic of inevitability
and fatalism,
to say that this is not inevitable,
and the best qualities of human nature
is when we step up and make a choice
about the future that we actually want
for the people and the world that we love.
There is no definition of wisdom,
in any tradition,
that does not involve restraint.
Restraint is the central feature
of what it means to be wise.
And AI is humanity's ultimate test
and greatest invitation
to step into our technological maturity.
There is no room
of adults working secretly
to make sure that this turns out OK.
We are the adults.
We have to be.
And I believe another choice
is possible with AI
if we can commonly recognize
what we have to do.
And eight years from now,
I'd like to come back to this stage,
not to talk about more
problems with technology,
but to celebrate how we stepped up
and solved this one.
Thank you.
(Applause and cheers)